If you're interested in an ice cream
calculator, then this video is for you
because we're going to look at a new one
[music] that is available for everybody
to use.
Scoopulator. It's a really difficult
word for me to say. It's a relatively
new ice calculator that is online. So, I
thought I'd give it a bash. And I got in
contact with the developer and he gave
me a bit of background. We'll talk about
that later. But today, we're going to
bring up the website, develop a really
quick gelato recipe, which is going to
be really simple for everybody to make,
and we'll talk about how to adjust a
recipe using this calculator as we go
through. This is my first time using it,
apart from adding two ingredients, which
are different here in Canada to what's
available on their website. Let's dig in
and see what it's like. So, this is what
the website looks like when you go on.
We're going to develop a gelato base.
So, we're going to select gelato from
the type. And here are your target
profiles. You can adjust these as you
go. And we'll do that as time goes on.
As you can see, the ice cream setting
has lots of various options, but today
we're doing gelato. So, let's stick with
that. We'll go through the others
another day. This is how it looks. Now,
you've got the gelato base target
profile. This is kind of what it looks
like here.
There are some basic recipes that you
can start with. I'm logged in because
I've had to add two main ingredients.
One is the whipping cream here which is
33% and the other one is the milk which
is 3.25%. So we start with the serving
temperature relative sweetness which is
important if you like all your ice cream
to be a similar sweetness level. Total
solids 36 to 43. This is for obviously
for gelato total fat and milk fat. Now,
I would actually have these reversed
because with people making ice creams
and gelatas with dairyfree ingredients,
that's going to really play havoc and
you'll have to go to the free form kind
of layout because personally, total fat
is easier to read. See here, if you go
free form, there's no targets for you.
So, it's harder to start with. So, if
you want to make a a vegan plant-based
whatever recipe, that's going to
struggle. So then you got sugars, milk
solids, non-fat, um, and stabilizers and
emulsifiers, alcohol. So let's start by
adding our milk. So you can just type in
milk and then just go through the whole
long list until you find the milk that
you want to use. You can add, like I
said, you can add whatever ingredient
you want in here, which is really nice.
USDA lists of, I don't know, millions of
different food types.
So you can just add the one that you
use. I'm just trying to find my user
one, but there it is. Whole milk 3.25%
user whipping cream. This I've added
this because that is what our cream here
is or that's what the cream I'm going to
use is 33% fat content. If you're in the
US, then you can add your heavy creams
like that. And if you're in the UK, a
beautiful thing, double cream. Yes. 48
and 50. So, you know, it depends on
where you buy it from. Sainsbury's is
50, Waitro is 48. So, you know, anyway,
we're going to add our sugar. We're
going to make this nice, easy recipe
that's kind of, you know, accessible to
everyone. Skin milk powder, super
important ingredient in proper luxury
ice cream making.
And we're going to flavor this with
something, but before that, we're going
to add a little bit of invert sugar or
glucose syrup, something like that. So,
we've got glucose, inverted sugar, corn
syrup, golden syrup. They're all
basically the same thing. Okay, but
we're going to flavor this with an
extract. It might not be vanilla
extract, but you can see it's here. So,
we can use that. I wonder what other
extracts are on here. So, let's just
type in extract and see what we got.
Almond and vanilla. Yeah, yeast extract
spread. So, that's, you know, like um
Marmite or Vegggemite. That's the kind
of breakdown and that tells you how much
it contributes to the freezing point
depression. So, that's a really
interesting little thing that pops up
there. So, we've got all the components
we need here. I might add stabilizer in
a little bit, but let's start. If we
click on that, we can actually see some
more information about that ingredient.
Opens up in a new web page. Really
interesting. 35% alcohol, 65% water.
Obviously, that water is likely in the
alcohol itself. So, that tells us the
the actual breakdown of it. So, let's
just start adding some numbers just to
get something on this target screen for
us to see. This won't be right. I
guarantee you, but you can see the
process.
You're trying to get on this website as
many things in green as possible.
Anything in a red is kind of a problem.
So, here we got 725 g. We can rescale
this really easily. So, this is also
really, really nice little feature. Just
we're going to do a ninja creamy deluxe.
So, we scale it to 750. Now, we got a
problem with our serving temperature.
We're at -20 Celsius. Way too low. So,
this actually would just really struggle
to freeze properly. So, the biggest
thing to to adjust this with is our
sugars. So, we can just reduce these bit
by bit until we get to the kind of level
that we need. I'm doing this slowly so
you can see and kind of understand where
things change. See the relative
sweetness starts changing as we reduce
our sucrose level. Obviously, the
vanilla extract changes our serving
temperature as well. So, our freezing
point, we can reduce that as well. We
can pop that down here. You see, we're
getting close now. We got our serving
temperature at minus4. Relative
sweetness is in the middle. And our
total solids are just a little bit low.
So, what we can do is start playing with
our things like our glucose syrup, our
granulated sugar, and our skim milk
powder.
And you can see we got our solids there,
but our serving temperatures still are
just a touch too high. Again, I really
wish that that total fat was accessible
target rather than milk fat, cuz then if
you want to make this with anything
other than dairy, that makes much more
sense. So, if you're the developer, add
that. Even just add it and keep the milk
fat so it's relative to both types of
people that are making it. those that
don't want dairy and those that do
because as you can see they're basically
the same. Our milk solids non-fats or
skim milk powder is being adjusted
along with our granulated sugar, our
glucose syrup and our vanilla extract to
kind of get to kind of get somewhere
where you know we're me I'm happy to be
14us 14.4 four. That's fine to be fair.
14.1. That's good enough. That's close
enough.
If we add goo,
then we can actually account for a
little bit more solids from that. So,
we're going to thicken that base up just
a touch. But as this is gelato, it has
much higher levels of stabilizer than
standard US ice cream. And that's just
due to the amount of fat that's in it.
So, we're at 7% fat right now. So, you
know, we're we're firmly in the middle.
Gelato can go down to like 2% fat. So,
with a reasonable place to start, we're
going to adjust this to 750 g batch.
That is a Ninja Creamy Deluxe. And there
we have our base recipe. This took
minutes to do. The vanilla extract is
out of the alcohol. We're not going to
use emulsifier. Here is another visual
interpretation of how your recipe looks
based on ingredients. And it gives it
percentages just like those squares
above. our sweetener breakdown. So,
where our sweetness comes from. [snorts]
And then we've got the visual rep
representation of our scoopability.
Um minus4 is my preferred serving
temperature because I don't have to wait
forever to scoop it out of the freezer.
Um that's the the serving temperature
there. And the freezing point is
important because that tells you when
it's going to start to freeze.
So that tells you at minus3 C your ice
cream your ice cream base will start to
solidify and freeze up which means that
it's going to freeze nicely without any
major issues. Sweetness level here 18%.
It gives you a visual comparison based
on other ones. So Danny Curry 18.4 David
Liberit's chocolate 22.84 A4 salt and
straw 16
underbelly. He doesn't like um
particularly sweet ice cream, so that
that doesn't surprise me. Um but here we
go. Let's get this written down and make
this gelato. Right, let's get everything
we need in this little container here.
We're going to start with our milk. 458
g. In goes our cream. 114 g. Because
we've got stabilizer in here, we're
going to weigh our sugar and skim milk
powder into a little container. 126 gram
of sugar, 38 gram of skim milk powder, 3
g of gua gum. So, gelato is is
thickened. Depending actually where you
where you get it, where you buy it, and
where it originates from, where that
recipe originates from, that will detect
the type of stabilizer that they use.
We're going to mini whisk that together.
So, again, we're just stirring that to
break up those little powder pieces in.
That goes into there. And let's stir
this together. We're not heating this
up. We're just going to stir it for a
couple of minutes to dissolve that sugar
and that milk powder.
With our sugar stirred in, we're going
to add our
5 g of glucose. And finally, our
extract. Today, I'm using
Watkins coffee extract.
That's it. That is our recipe.
I'm going to pop this into our Ninja
Creamy container. Again, super easy
recipe.
This is
This is to highlight the calculator.
This recipe isn't going to break any
records. This is a super simple recipe
to show you the ice cream calculator.
So, with that in there, we are now ready
to put this in the freezer overnight to
harden off. So, while that is hardening
off, let's talk about the calculator a
little bit more. This was developed by a
software engineer called Malachi Wy from
San Francisco. He likes to do things
like pottery, 3D printing, cooking,
similar things to me to be fair. And he
got into ice cream a few years ago and
wanted to use his desire to create super
nice, attractive interfaces on the
internet and software. So that's kind of
what he did. He's been on Reddit for a
long time and obviously looked at
Underbelly and then developed this
calculator, put it on Reddit and then
got some really good feedback and then
developed it further into what it is
today. The main reason for development
was because he realized that a lot of
the other calculators of which there
aren't that many to still to be fair.
they're not particularly user friendly,
especially for beginners. And that is
actually the case and that's why he
developed this so that it was accessible
to beginners and people that had a
little bit more experience using such
software. So far, it it's really easy to
use, which is why I'm making this video.
I have my own that I use, but there's
very few other options that I get people
message me maybe once a month saying,
"I've developed an ice cream
calculator." And you go and have a look
and they're really poor. They're badly
designed. They're really difficult to
use. And nobody that is new to ice cream
or even software is going to have any
clue how as to how to use it. So going
to Scoopulator and actually logging in,
inputting two of my own ingredients and
then developing that first recipe for
you guys here in real [clears throat]
time whilst we're doing it, it was super
easy. So that's really nice thing to to
see from a brand new piece of software.
So that's the basics as to why it
exists. I absolutely know. I mean, the
amount of ice cream I've made over the
years, I know when a recipe is going to
turn out well. And there's a couple of
things I would suggest are changed. But
that's not because of me being a funny
old bastard, but because people like to
make ice cream using different
ingredients these days. That fat milk
fat thing for gelato, that needs to be
changed because not everyone wants to
use dairy. So if you try and develop a
recipe for gelato, even though
technically it wouldn't be gelato
because there's no dairy in it, you
still want to be able to make that. The
gelato
format still stays. It still remains
with that lower fat, higher
stabilization,
etc. So we need to kind of adapt to to
suit people as best as we can. That's a
simple change. Other than that, really
like this calculator so far. Let's get
this out of the freezer and get it
spinning. Right,
let's get this spun up. It's actually
like two days later, but here we go.
Just noticed this is another new apron,
but it's made for short ass people
because if I lift this up, obviously
it's got the adjusters here. If I lift
this up, the straps, which are already
here, come all the way up to here. So,
unless you're 5'5 in tall or shorter,
you're going to have the straps around
your armpits. And I refuse to spend $150
on a bloody apron. So, I'm just going to
keep moaning about it.
[music]
>> [music]
>> So, this video was never about making
this ice cream. I mean, it's just a very
basic ice cream using coffee extract. It
although this is the most perfect scoop
of ice cream I think I've ever done.
Perfectly smooth reflective surface.
God, glasses are sliding down my face.
It's never about this ice cream. in this
video. This is about the introduction to
Scupulator ice cream calculator. Um,
I've been using Scupulator for the last
few days to try and understand a bit
more about how its processes work and
how it develops its recipes. It's not
perfect, but none of them are, but it is
a really really good one and it's
available to everyone being a web-based
platform. So, if you are interested in
learning how to use Scupulator, let me
know in the comments. Don't forget to
like and subscribe to this video. And
next week I will do a full tutorial on
how to use scupulator ice cream
calculator. It's a mouthful. And all the
interesties of adding your own
ingredients and what it means to balance
a recipe. Because what we will do is
create that black forest ice cream
[music] that is right up there on my top
five using scupil and you can understand
a bit more about the process. So again,
don't forget to like and subscribe.
Comment down below. See you next week.
[music]